Guide to the Elaine Frank Davison Germans from Russia collection 1900-2000
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Elaine Frank Davison Germans from Russia collection
1900-2000
1970-2000
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Davison, Elaine Frank
WCMss.020
8 linear feet 8 boxes
This collection contains interviews on cassette tapes, publications, research files, and family correspondence pertaining to Germans from Russia created by a genealogist from Walla Walla, Washington.
Collection is open for research.
Donated to the Whitman College and Northwest Archives by Julie Davison Loiacono in January 2003. The accession number is retro-0015.
Elaine Frank Davison was born in Walla Walla, Washington on August 23, 1929 to Johann Conrad and Maria Catherine Frank, Germans from Russia who immigrated to the United States in 1905. She was the youngest of eight children. Her interest in the stories of the Volga Germans was piqued by her father's stories of his homeland. Upon his death in 1959, she took up genealogical research. Ultimately, she became responsible for recovering and preserving the history of her family's home village of Kautz / Werschinka. Davison spent her childhood in Walla Walla. After graduating from high school, she worked for the Pacific Telephone and Telegraph company. In 1949, she married George Hite Davison, and the couple moved to Spokane, Washington. They had four children: James Hite, Loralee, Julie Ann, and Karla Elaine. Elaine returned to work in 1960 at Sacred Heart Hospital in Spokane. The family returned to Walla Walla in 1963, where Elaine began working as a medical transcriptionist.
A self-taught researcher and writer, Davison self-published books about the village, entitled "Unsere Leute von Kautz" (Our People from Kautz). Her "Kautz Project" required numerous oral history interviews, as many of the relevant genealogical records remain in Germany and Russia. In 1990, Davison and her work were featured in "Making a Difference: A Centennial Celebration of Washington Women, Volume II," a curriculum handbook created by the Office of the Superintendent of Public Instruction.
Elaine Frank Davison died on March 17, 2001.
The collection, which consists of Elaine Frank Davison's research files and publications, is divided into six series: Sound Recordings, Publications by Elaine Davison, Genealogical Research, Correspondence, Obituaries, and Miscellaneous. It is a rich source of information for both genealogists and researchers interested in the immigration and ethnic history of Eastern Washington.
"Laurel's Story: A Montana Heritage" by Elsie P. Johnston (1979) and issues of "Der Kirchenbote / The Christian Messenger" from the 1950s-1970s were transferred to the Acquisitions Department of Penrose Library.
Rempel, Arthur G. (Arthur Gustav)
Frank family; Rempel family
Washington (State); German Americans
- Sound Recordings, 1973-1997; 1; 3 linear feet 3 boxes
  The Sound Recording Series consists of 262 cassette tapes of interviews and lectures relating to Davison's research on Germans from Russia. An inventory of the Sound Recordings Series is available in Box 1 of the collection.
  - Cassette Tapes, 1-95, 1975-1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Cassette Tapes, 96-185, 1973-1997, undated (Box 2)
  - Cassette Tapes, 186-262, 1973-1998 (Box 3)
- Publications by Elaine Davison, 1978-1998; 2; 0.2 linear feet 7 folders
  The Publications by Elaine Davison Series includes eight volumes of Unsere Leute von Kautz, a compilation of photocopies marriage license returns for Germans from Russia in Walla Walla County, 1891-1912, and the text of a speech delivered in 1998.
  - "Unsere Leute von Kautz", 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - "Early Marriage License returns of Germans from Russia in Walla Walla County, Washington, 1891-1912", 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Realizing My Dream", 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Genealogical Research Files, 1900-2000; 3; 2.5 linear feet approximately 3 boxes
  The Genealogical Research Series contains research files on specific families in Washington and Montana, publications (most issued by various historical societies), and reprinted censuses from various German colonies in the Volga region. Many of the materials about the Rempel family were written by Arthur B. Rempel, a member of Whitman College faculty from 1938-1975.
  - American Historical Society of Germans from Russia Newsletter, 1971-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - "Hussenback Review", 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Jeruslan Nachrichten", 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Ragas Report, 1997-1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Descriptions of the Saratov Colonies of Oleshna / Dietel, Grechinaua Luka / Walter, Karamyshevka / Bauer, and Yelshanka / Husaren in 1798, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Descriptions of the Saratov Colonies of Yagodnaya Polyana, Pamyatnaya / Rothammel, and Linevo Ozero / Hussenbach, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Deutsches Namenlexikon", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - HEMEЦКИE КОЛОНИИ НА ВОЛГЕ, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Logan County, Colorado Cemetery Survey", 1984 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Yellowstone County Montana Cemeteries" Vol. 1, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Yellowstone County Montana Cemeteries" Vol. 2, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Beyond the Gates: A Tribute to those Uprooted Emigrants from Merkel, Russia and neighboring colonies Whose Insight Sought Freedom in Foreign Lands. A Memorial to Those Who Stayed Behind.", 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Sod 'N Seed 'N Tumbleweed: A History of the Huntley Project", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Usere Leute von Walter" Number 2, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Index to Place Names Found in "from Catherine to Khrushchev", 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Long Meadows", by Minnie Hite Moody, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Too Far to Go Back: Wagons West and the Germans from Russia", 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Goly Karamysh / Balzer 1775 and 1798 Census Revisions, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Norka 1811 Census Revision, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Neu-Hussenback 1857/1858 Census, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Norka / Weigand 1775 and 1798 Censuses, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Kolb 1798-1858 Censuses, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pobochnaya 1772 and 1798 documents, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Gololobovka / Dönhof 1775 and 1798 Censuses, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Splavnukha / Huck 1775 and 1798 Censuses, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Popovka / Kutter 1775 and 1798 Censuses, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ust-Zolikha / Messer 1775 and 1798 Censuses, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Susly / Herzog 1798 documents, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Lesnoy Karamysh / Grimm 1775 and 1798 Censuses, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Frank Family: Lineages Report, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Frank, John David and Elizabeth Family Record, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Frank Family Reunion Invitation, [1982] (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Frank, John George Family Tree, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Frank, Carl G. Life Story, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Frank, Alexander Experiences of, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Frank Family, Biography of, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Frank Family Genealogy / Christ Lutheran Church Records, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Frank, Johann Conrad Family File, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Interviews with Wilhelm "William" Frank, "Uncle Bill", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Interview with Uncle Bill, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Statuten- und Protokollbuch der Evang. St. Paulsgemeinde in Walla Walla, Wash, 1907 (photocopy), 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Some Experiences of My Life" by Emil Weissner, Sr., 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notes from Trip to USSR and Volga Colonies, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mary Gally, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miller Family Tree, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Rempel Trilogy, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "The Story of Greta" by Arthur G. Rempel, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Memories" by Arthur G. Rempel, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rempel, Miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Apropos to H. G. Rempel's Diary, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "My Trip to America: the Diary of Evangeline G. Rempel, 1922-1923", 1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - A Family in Exile at a Labor camp, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - George Steinmetz Families, 1900-1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1913-1982; 4; 0.2 linear feet 8 folders
  The Correspondence Series contains letters in English, Russian, and German exchanged among Elaine Frank Davison and various family members. Many of the letters in German and Russian are translated.
  - Correspondence from Siberia (Dines Frank / Amalia Frank), 1913-1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Siberia, Copies and Translations, 1975-1982 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - Correspondence from Russia to William Frank, 1969-1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence from Dinis Frank to William Frank, 1969-1982 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence to Katharine Benzel, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1974-1982 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
- Obituaries, 1920-1997; 5; 2 linear feet 2 boxes
  The Obituaries Series consist primarily of photocopies of newspaper obituaries of Volga Germans from Russia who resided in Walla Walla, Washington; Yakima, Washington; Laurel, Montana; and Billings, Montana.
  - Obituaries A-J, 1920-1997 (Box 7)
  - Obituaries K-Z, 1920-1997 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous, 1981-1998; 6; 0.1 linear feet 4 folders
  Miscellaneous items in the collection include photographs and a photo album, maps of Russia, and a clipping file.
  - Maps, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Album, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, 1990-1998 (Box 6, Folder 26)